this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software
hello this is two beers for software
engineering radio in this episode I am
talking to the CTO and founder of lucid
Burks grant Ingersoll as you know from
earlier episodes he is connected to
Apache projects like Lusine solar and
mahout together with Thomas Morton and
Andrew Farriss grant wrote a book
entitled taming text how to find
organized and manipulated and almost one
year after being published I will talk
with him about the book and its
influence on the community on this show
grant thanks for being on the show thank
you glad to be here again
I think you have heard of the Turing
test being passed in June 2014 and for
our listeners there was this guy called
eugene goostman who passed the Turing
test who was just chatting around with
people from all over the world but in
the end it was a chatbot and not a real
person and so that was kind of the core
of the Turing test and I think you
should have been partying after hearing
this or what were your thoughts what
were your reactions on this Turing test
yeah I should have been party and yeah
no I mean I think it's it's obviously a
great advancement and I think it speaks
to you know a lot of the effort that has
been going into artificial intelligence
machine learning natural language
processing you know a lot of the things
obviously I'm trying to cover in my book
I don't think this stuff in the book you
know quite passes the Turing test yet
but I do think it kind of lays the
foundation for a lot of those things and
so yeah I mean I think I think it's a
it's a great advancement I
I think still a long ways to go in terms
of you know being general-purpose enough
to handle all language in all situations
but it's really a good step in the right
direction
were there any products you are involved
in part of the solution do you know any
particular stuff there no I'm not
actually familiar at the low level with
what they did so but I would imagine
it's you know a good chunk of open
source along with some of their own
mixed in kind of things so yeah let's
hope it gets back to the open source
community then so everyone can learn
from it and use the libraries but then
let's get to the the core meaning of
this show which is talking about your
book timing text which is which has been
released at the end of last year if I'm
correct and I know that you are actually
working on a second version right now is
that correct or is it wrong by now I
know we are slowly working on a second
version you know as you listeners of
this show may know I'm also involved in
a startup so as always writing a book is
a long and laborious process but yeah we
are ready in a second edition although
you know the first edition continues to
do well and continue to get good
feedback there and I think well some of
the examples are uh could be are going
to be updated you know the core concepts
are still really solid and in the in the
first edition okay yeah well we'll be
going back to this in a couple of
minutes before that I'd like to ask you
why did you actually write the book what
was the reason why did you get to the
topic of taming text of processing texts
and to writing a book about that yeah
that's a great question there's actually
I think kind of two levels one it it's
the book I wish I had when I started or
at least it's an attempt at the book I
wish I had when I started which is you
know my target audience and our target
audience with
taming text was really developers who
you know that you're good programmer but
aren't necessarily familiar with search
and natural language processing and
programming and so you wanted something
that could help you get going on the
examples the concepts the ideas also
leveraging a lot of the strong
open-source capabilities out there and
really to be honest without the you know
the math and the kind of the dense
academic rigor that a lot of the books
in this field have because frankly I
think a lot of Engineers simply don't
have time to dig into all the formulas
because let's face it they've got
problems they want to solve and so they
want realistic ways to get those done
not necessarily worried at first about
the theory behind it they would rather
go and explore it second you know it was
just thinking the second area kind of is
obviously a bit more personal but you
know career-wise I was looking for
something to help you know help me along
on my career and frankly I think having
a book writing a book can be something
that can help boost your career and your
standing in the community and things
like that and so you know it's
definitely been very helpful for my
career as well but a big effort I think
to to boost your career since I think I
couldn't manage to write a book about
anything in the end ya know I mean you'd
be surprised
you know first off there's a real thirst
for technical books you know I think the
publishers are technical books are
always looking for authors so it is it
is definitely a labor of love as they
say it's not something that you make
money off of directly although you know
I mean I obviously I have received some
royalties for it but you know it's not
like you're writing the you know the
Great American Novel or you know the
next New York Times bestseller here and
so you very much have to go into it as
this is something I love to do or I want
to do and then you know you've it is
hard you've got to put in a lot of time
into it and you've got to figure out how
to speak to users in a way that their
readers in a way that they're going to
understand you know I don't you know
obviously the the public and judge
I think we did a good job at it but you
know ultimately other people are the
judge of that yes for sure
based on the feedback what are your
listeners actually working on or to put
it in another phrase um why are they
buying your book and reading it yeah I
mean I think you know the you mentioned
I think the readers are definitely
engineers they're often Java programmers
they're off there they're getting
started in this field you know I see
this time and time again at lucid works
my company where we go into an
organization we're helping them with a
lot of these issues like search machine
learning natural language processing
there's usually one or two people
they're often the boss or a PhD or
somebody who's really experienced in the
field who knows search and all that and
then they've got a bunch of other
engineers who are good strong
programmers but just getting started
with these particular kinds of problems
and so they're you know they're buying
it because it helps them get up that
learning curve you know as I mentioned
earlier this is not the it is not a book
for experts it's very much a book for
beginners or mid-level people or people
who want to have deeper knowledge on
some of the open source libraries that
we cover and so I think a lot of the
feedback we get is along those lines hey
great book for helping me get started
meanwhile you know the experts are
saying yeah you know I already knew that
which is which is fine that that tells
me we hit our target target audience
right on that's good do you also hear
phrases like well we will buy a Google
blade and that's it for us and what are
your thoughts and about that
so like Google Search Appliance yes you
mean you know I mean there's a time and
place for that obviously I think that's
much more of a black box situation it's
you know really set up and designed for
kind of low end search around you know
your corporate intranet what you know we
see time and time again the reason why
people are selecting technologies like
solar and leucine and
and open an opinion out and others is
they have a problem that's much harder
to solve they have a problem that they
want to have control over they want to
know how the inner workings happen they
want to be able to control those inner
workings alter those inner workings they
also want to be able to more effectively
monetize or more efficiently deal with
their data so you know black box doesn't
do that for you whereas when you've got
open source it's the you know
essentially the ultimate white box right
and so I can dig in if I need to but I
don't have to and so you know it really
helps them solve much harder problems
that I don't think you can with just a
black box type approach can you give at
least one example of these this kind of
problems they want to solve which is not
simply searching your internet or other
easy data files or whatever you know I
think there's lots of great examples out
there ecommerce is probably one of the
strongest ones where you know you're
there are so many signals coming in from
your users your buyers the general web
public all of that kind of stuff that
you want to then incorporate into the
way you return search results so you
know somebody comes in and searches for
TVs you want to be able to rank those
results according to lots of different
criterias that goes well beyond just hey
does the word TV match I remember a few
years back one of our customers who was
on public record was sheet music plus
you know they're I think one of the
world's largest purveyors of you know
sheet music ranging from you know modern
rock and roll all the way back to
Beethoven Bach etc and when one of their
top queries against their search index
was simply the word piano now you tell
me what should I return for search
results when somebody types in the word
piano it's usually quite straightforward
if they type in you know
Beethoven's Ninth Symphony and whatever
you know for harpsichord or whatever it
is right but if somebody just types in
piano what should I return
and so what companies like that want to
be able to do is leverage all of these
different factors these these features
signals if you will that help them
figure out what they should return
because in fact users time and time
again are telling them what they want to
see when they search for a piano they
want to see the most popular piano items
maybe the company wants to overlay in
that the items that they make the most
money on etc etc and so all of those
things factored in to an overall ranking
that they want to be able to control and
manipulate so that they can ultimately
keep their users happy as well as
obviously increase their profits yes
understood getting back to your book
timing texts what tools do you use to
tame text in the book and maybe in your
real life as well and why are you
choosing exactly those tools I think the
tools people are using you know first
off the book is really geared towards
each chapter presents a concept like
search or named entity recognition or
clustering and and lays out the concepts
behind those in in layman's terms or
engineering terms at least and then we
go into an example of some open source
that helps solve those problems so for
search we use Lucene and solar for
clustering and and some classification
problems we use mahout and a few other
libraries for things like string
matching we actually roll some of our
own examples but you know primarily
speaking there we chose open source
libraries that have commercially
friendly licenses like the apache
license or the bsd license things like
that and they're also just happen to be
projects that we think are pretty
popular and also projects were
intimately familiar with so you know
leucine solar mahout open NLP and then a
few others coming on and then in the new
version the second
version will also be added in there as
well so you know I tend to use in my
day-to-day job a lot of leucine and
solar I also use a variety of open
source natural language processing tools
and then you know supplement that with
stuff that we build ourselves your book
elaborates a lot about search engines
and their use and how to adjust them and
so I'd like to ask you the question how
do those search engines actually judge
or adjust the quality of their results
is there the difference between
multi-purpose search engines and single
purpose search engines and are there
some different approaches in there you
know that's a great question I mean I
think you know obviously I can't speak
to you know how Google are some of the
large engines you know they don't reveal
all of their secret sauce but you know
generally speaking the way you know
there's a couple of different approaches
to determining whether a document is
relevant or not and then of course once
you determine if something's relevant or
not then it's just simply a matter of
taking that score and sorting by that
such that you return out a ranked list
of results you know the main two ways
one is a probabilistic way which is
essentially saying what is the
probability that this document answers
this query and there's other you can
actually flip that on that head and say
what is the probability that this query
matches this document and so there's
there's different approaches to that and
there's a couple of different
open-source engines out there that
support those including Lucene the other
one and often the the more commonly
implemented one is what's called a
vector space model and if you think back
to your high school mathematics classes
you can essentially think of the vector
space model is you've got a vector
representing the document in an
n-dimensional space and then you've got
a vector representing the query in that
same n-dimensional space if you put
their tails together that forms an angle
if you take the cosine of that angle
you get a score between minus 1 and 1
and so if if you remember your math
again correctly when the angle is 0 the
cosine is 1 and so intuitively speaking
you would think that since those two and
those two vectors are exactly the same
they should be a very high match in
reality you know we take that model and
modify it we add boolean logic on top of
it we add a lots of other scoring
factors that you can bring into play to
essentially help you do that ranking and
then what you know is often done is you
have you have data sets that you
quote-unquote practice against that
allows you to determine whether your
rankings are good enough or not and then
you may actually have rules that you
overlay on top of that too and you know
big companies like Google and the like I
mean they have hundreds if not thousands
of people who work on and manipulate
those rankings you know throughout the
day throughout the year such that
they're you know trying to improve that
user feedback loop if you will so they
are actually doing some sort of a B test
here and say ok this and that changed
and this is a good good result or a bad
result or in how are they actually doing
it yeah actually ABCD efg that you know
I mean I think from what I've seen and
understand the large majority of users
in internet search engines are in an
experiment at any given point in time
and so actually you know a small
percentage in I don't know what the
exact numbers are here I've heard you
know that it's roughly 10% of users see
the what is considered to be the best
version of that internet search engine
at any given point in time and everybody
else is in is in an experiment and those
experiments may be anything ranging from
changing the color of you know an icon
to changing the font to changing the
actual scoring algorithm
and so they're constantly looking for
ways to tweak the search results and you
know ultimately they're you know looking
for a ways to balance and increase well
increase the amount of ads clicked
relative to the results that they're
displaying right so obviously they have
different goals than just necessarily
providing you with the absolute best
results that answer your question they
also want to make sure you're they want
to increase the likelihood that you're
going to click on an ad as well right so
you know there's lots of things that go
into to calculating that but yeah at the
end of the day we're all and we're all
in a big experiment all right and how
important is the actual position or rank
of an item within the result set and is
there a difference between general
purpose search engines like Google or
Bing and special systems for a certain
user group for instance scientists or so
yeah I mean I think you know a cover of
this affair but in the search chapter of
the book but I mean I think it really
the answer is it depends not to cop out
but you know there's been a lot of
academic study of this and I think at
the end of the day it depends on the
user and what the user is expecting I
think often the reason why search
engines fail is they fail to capture
what what a user really wants or needs
and so you know that is that that
understanding comes from thinking about
what your who your user is right so if
if I'm you know Joe consumer on the
internet and I'm just looking for you
know a TV or something like that then
you know they're there if they just put
in a generic term then you know they're
probably not going to be too upset if
the TV they actually end up buying is in
the fifth slot as opposed to the first
slot or even perhaps on the second page
although that's not as likely but if
they put in a very specific kind of TV
you know with very specific attributes
you know they want a 57 inch Sony
whatever whatever with you know 3d
hologram projections right
and that one they know it exists and it
doesn't come up then they're going to be
upset right and and perhaps go look
elsewhere similarly if you're you know
working for a competitive intelligence
situation or if you're trying to find
terrorists or other bad guys you know
your criteria for the results is often
very different because you're obviously
invested very deeply in making sure you
find that needle in the haystack so
you're often willing to read a lot more
results you're often willing to spend a
lot more time adjusting your queries and
and tinkering with the way you look at
the results so that you can try to find
that you know proverbial needle in a
haystack that you know helps you catch
the bad guy or prevent something bad
from happening right yeah and just just
because I'm a bit related to it and
things like a discovery it's kind of the
same you're just not allowed to have
something being lost yeah I mean if you
think about it like 'hey discovery or
legal situations like if you if you hand
over a bunch of emails that you didn't
know talked about you know a company
doing something bad and then you hand
that over to the prosecution or the
other side you know that's the that's
the smoking gun right and so then you're
you're going to be in big trouble that's
right yeah you want you don't want to do
this kids need to learn to understand
texts why growing up and machines to of
course but is it the goal to actually
preserve the computer state of mind or
to enable every machine to build up the
database and learn again so or is there
something in between well I mean I think
if if the computer is learning a model
you certainly would behoove you to not
forget the model unless you decide that
that model is just not a very good one
so you know there are systems that kind
of take a genetic or a never
Ellucian area approach to learning and
so they throw away old models that
aren't deemed as good as newer models
but you know that's still diff you know
they'll they'll still keep the model
they have you know that you know if they
were to shut down or restart they would
still have that model preserved you know
there's also obviously you know kind of
the bootstrapping problem one would face
when going into a new environment so you
know if if the Machine if you've trained
it on them a certain model and then
you've deployed it in this situation
where it's capable of learning but you
know that original model is not very
good you obviously would end up you know
either right away or as you learn more
throw out that older model or at least
adapt that model but I'm not as familiar
with ones that you know just lose their
you know in memory state and then have
to reboot strap themselves the next time
they come up I mean that that doesn't
strike me as necessarily a good approach
but maybe I'm missing something there
okay it might be because I'm thinking of
systems that replicate themselves and
just have a small amount of data but
need to actually be precise and their
results yeah I mean I think that's one
of the benefits of you know I mean if
you're especially comparing it to people
right I mean in theory the replication
of knowledge on a computer is you know
significantly faster than it is in the
human race right you know I mean think
takes us years and years to learn you
know for kids to to become on par and
intelligence with adults right whereas
you know presumably once a computer has
learned something if it truly is
learning in the same sense you know we
can then clone it quite quickly because
it's all digital and electronic you know
I mean I think perhaps what you're
getting at to do is a lot of times you
know you're you're obviously you're
building a model right
so that model is a representation of the
raw data or the data that it's seen so
far and so that model often ends up
being obviously a lot smaller than the
original data and so then you know we
can go and replicate that model across
lots of machines right and so in some
regards there your each machine has a
base starting model that it can come
from and then it learns new based off of
what it sees right and then you know
sometimes you'll have algorithms that
actually sink them back up and figure
out which one's the most you know the
most efficient one that's going to where
that evolutionary approach I talked
about earlier can come in so you know
and then there's also you know a lot of
work being done these days and what's
quote-unquote called deep learning and
so you know that can also be that's all
about just bootstrapping from very
little training if you will just
bootstrapping from you know what it sees
and trying to figure out the
relationships without actually having
somebody tell it what the relationships
are getting into some more advanced and
maybe real life aspects of in inverted
commas taming text now I'd like to get
to some chapters of your book
the first one is fuzzy string matching
what is fuzzy string matching and why is
this important for our day-to-day search
life yeah that's a great question I mean
this is actually one of the chapters we
debated as to whether you know quite
heavily debated as whether it belongs in
the book or not and ultimately obviously
we decided it did I think you know
string matching you know just
straight-up matching you know two words
that are equal or not is obviously
pretty well understood and it's a rather
simple function on you know in Java like
a string object or in C or whatever
right and that's all well and good for
when you have exact matches but as as we
all know the world is not exact and so
there's often fuzziness people misspell
things people
make all kinds of errors you have
problems like if you're scanning in
image it you know documents and then you
do OCR the OCR process can be noisy and
so there's just all these places in
times where text is fuzzy for lack of a
better word like we just don't know
whether it exactly matches and so we
need algorithms that help us deal with
that situation right and so that
particular chapter helps users
understand different algorithms for
calculating how similar individual words
our individual strings are and then
using those judgments to then you know
kind of cede the rest of the the
techniques in the book right so if you
know you know if you say for instance
you're dealing with certain kinds of
users who always misspell your last name
or misspelled the name of your product
you know for instance a classic one in
in is that people spell iPod like
they'll spell out I space-pod that's
about I - pod spell out I capital p OD
etc etc and so at the end of the day you
know you still want to match what
they're after which is the actual iPod
and so you need some of these techniques
to help you deal with those situations
and really it's it's then the feeds into
something like a search engine or your
your NLP system etc is kind of a
baseline of pre-processing but you know
in that chapter we also talked about how
how to give users things like
autosuggest
features you know so if you start typing
in a word it will help you autocomplete
that that's a way of helping guide your
users to good content that they you know
exists and will be helpful to them as
opposed to just letting them put in a
mistyped word and then wondering why the
results aren't any good but when I am
thinking of using fuzzy string matching
on single purpose search engines like
those scientific research databases I
would expect the results to be sometimes
weird
or even wrong especially if the system
thinks I spelled this term wrong but I
actually didn't how do you deal with
those situations do these algorithms and
able establishing feedback channels or
other ways of adjusting the result set
yeah yeah no that's a great question and
and and you're definitely right on I
mean I think you know this is why it's
called fuzzy string matching right is
there's inherently a score or
probability here that says here's the
degree to which we think this is correct
and I you know I always kind of have
this saying there's a there's a reason
why the same is the numbers don't lie
not the text doesn't lie because text
lies all the time and users lie all the
time not lying necessarily a malicious
way but lie in the sense that they don't
know how to spell or maybe they do know
how to spell but you you don't know how
to spell right or your algorithm doesn't
know how to spell or your data doesn't
know how to spell and so you always have
this fuzziness factor going on in pretty
much everything you do in this space
right whether it's search or machine
learning natural language processing
it's all essentially about coming up
with a score you know a degree of
likelihood or a degree of relevance and
so I think the best systems are able to
incorporate how users interact with that
fuzziness in a way that helps them
ultimately get to their answer even if
the any individual answer is not correct
right so if if an engine just says oh
here's your answer and the user looks at
it and says sorry I know it's not then
you know that that application has
failed but if the application says you
know here's what we think is your answer
but you know perhaps here's some other
suggestions or here's some ways that you
might refine your your question that
usually is more successful and of course
things like autocomplete also help
preempt that so that the user can see
right off the bat as they're typing and
then adjust on the fly so that they you
know they get to the what they're
looking for faster because like I said
at the end of the day it's all it's all
up to that user to decide what's what's
relevant and what's not
if we go to the actually next chapter in
your book after fuzzy string matching I
think there might be a connection
between the two since it is called
identifying people places and things I
think that sometimes the two topics
fuzzy string matching and finding
entities can be in contrary to each
other because entity names tend to not
look like the system thinks they should
don't they yeah I mean you know with
this chapter it's all about you know
identifying people places currencies you
know the things that I think we all
inherently do or learn you know when we
learn you know our native language or
learn a language right you recognize the
patterns that say you know this is
Tobias Katz or this is I Triple E or
this is lucid works right you know the
indicators that lead to that you know I
mean I think the challenge here again is
how do I help find those things because
you know let's face it like proper nouns
and the like are often very useful for
us as humans in understanding what a
particular document is about so if we
know it mentions people or places or
things there's that familiarity with it
and there's that reasoning that we can
do about it
and so I think it becomes really
important to have tools that help you do
those kinds of things and obviously you
know the the fuzziness here is is often
with the fact that you know let's face
it the most of us you know are never
mentioned in public content so the odds
of a computer or a learning model you
know a learning system ever seen a
particular mention of a person's name
you know especially if it's a non or
less common spelling is pretty low right
you know it's one thing to get Beyonce
correct it's another thing to get you
know you know Joe Smith or you know
whatever his name is who lives you know
down the street from you and and you can
never pronounce his name right so yeah
so there is an inherent
again fuzziness there but thankfully the
you know the languages do have some
structure to them and despite the fact
that everybody calls it unstructured
content I think language is actually one
of the most structured it's just that
we're not very good at teaching
computers how to deal with that
structure and so we're often stuck again
like you said with with these fuzzy
states that were in of yeah I think this
is a proper name but I'm not a hundred
percent certain right yeah and but I'm
going through your book I still think
that from this chapter on you are
talking about the more important but
harder problems and challenges you have
in actually understanding real text it's
not that you just understand a word and
can say okay this is a proper noun or
whatever in a sentence in in the biggest
yeah realm you now want to get things in
in context and I want to you know find
out which is a what entity is a place
and and how this relates to the rest of
the text so how do you face those
challenges now know that you can't
really go to one world a word and and
until what actually role it had plays in
a sentence yeah it's definitely the
challenge here and I mean frankly this
is what I love about this space and why
it's so interesting and exciting because
because it is hard you know the book I
think we definitely progress through you
know more or less how you know things
get harder as we go through the book you
know ultimately you know the the second
to last chapter is about actually
building a fact-based question-answering
system you know what you could kind of
think of as a really lightweight version
of IBM Watson or Google now or Siri kind
of functionality and then you know the
last chapter actually is hey here's all
the really hard stuff that you know you
could write a whole book on just those
things as well and and we kind of left
that as is you know the sky is really
the limit here when it comes to
exploring these I mean I think we're
seeing
all the time systems are getting better
and better at this but there's still
just a long way to go and you know like
I said this is this is where it gets
really fun right because you know
ultimately if you're not working on hard
problems you know you're probably not
going to be working very long at least
not in that field right well and kind of
the lower level of functions are pretty
well understood in terms of you know an
individual word but you know there's
still even problems there you've got
things like character encodings etc but
once we start moving up the the stack
there if you will to the semantic layer
and the discourse layer and some of
these higher levels of language where
you know there's there's a lot that's
not said in a particular document or the
way a user speaks that is either common
knowledge or maybe is delivered in its
sarcastically so on paper or in a you
know electronic form that sarcasm
doesn't necessarily come across and so
you know those present really hard
challenges for us as people trying to
write computer programs that understand
this kind of stuff that's right but
still really challenging for me to
actually think about having things like
QA machines or whatever that's so so
cool to see what comes out of it right
now right you know if you think about is
we're still kind of in its infancy I
mean I think ultimately you know QA is
where people what people mostly want you
know instead of having to cipher you
know sift through ten blue links and
that kind of stuff they want you know
when they ask a question they want what
they think is an answer but you know
that answer can be quite complex right
you know it's one thing to say who is
the president of United States right now
you know and answer that it's another
thing to ask the question you know what
are the reasons for the war in
fill-in-the-blank country right and and
to be able to ask that kind of question
of a computer is really interesting as
well and it's also just frankly really
hard to get back you know a college and
answer there because you know it
involves so many complex ideas and in
different opinions and
of those things and ultimately you know
that's what we as humans want to be able
to do as well but you know let's face it
we can't get through all of the data
there is to be able to always know the
right answer what do you think IBM
Watson Siri Google now you name it it's
this approach scalable so do you think
that those engines will get better and
better and better or do you think that
we need to have a switch in in
technologies or switch in approaches to
actually face the real challenges no I
mean I think you see them getting better
all the time I mean this is that whole
collective intelligence approach to
dealing with this kind of data which is
you know again we're making you know
educated guesses if you will based off
of what other similar people did right
and so and then trying to overlay some
personalization on it I mean I think
they're great examples of the state of
the art these days and and they are
getting better and will continue to be
there will continue to be a lot of
investment in those kinds of systems
because you know ultimately I think what
we are looking for is is tools and
approaches and and things like that that
complement us I'd take take away the
mundane tasks from us so that we can
focus on the harder challenges etc and
ultimately you know make our lives
easier better safer more efficient
whatever you know whatever kind of your
personal goals are so yeah I think
you're gonna see a continued evolution
there I don't know if it's really hard
to predict revolution so it may be the
case that there will be one you know 10
years ago I think you know Siri probably
or Google now or Watson was really hard
to obtain those kinds of results whereas
now it's you know much more practical
yeah definitely did you actually work on
a system like that or on QA systems how
did they look like and what problem did
they solve yes I worked on
back when I was at the Center for
natural language processing we worked on
a couple of different QA systems I also
worked on things like cross language
information retrieval and stuff like
that you know the book the last example
in there is a fairly basic QA system it
does reasonably well when you give it a
good set of facts and you know it pretty
much is only targeted towards answering
those facts there's actually a lot of
improvements that can be made to that if
you read like the Watson paper you know
a lot of the core foundation of what
they're doing is is the similar to the
approach that we're doing obviously
they're doing it in a much bigger scale
and with a lot more data on and more
sophisticated algorithms but the core of
it of of taking a user's query trying to
figure out what that query is about
right you know what that question is
about is it looking for a person is it
looking for a place is it looking for
some particular answer type classifying
so classifying that question into an
answer type and then using that to go do
a search and in fact IBM Watson actually
uses Lucine underneath the hood to do
that initial passage retrieval so that
gives you a candidate set of documents
that you know the computer says hey I
think one of these documents is going to
answer this question and then
essentially doing that post you know
taking those passages and scoring them
according to the likelihood and kind of
parsing parsing those windows or those
passages apart into into an answer is
what is happening underneath the hood
and Watson obviously again more
sophisticated than what we do in the
book but in the book we provide a pretty
simplistic approach to doing that which
works reasonably well and then you know
you can immediately see all kinds of
ways that you can improve it so you know
I think then you know one of the keys is
taking that and having kind of feedback
mechanisms built in such that you can
learn as you go from you know what
what's right and what's wrong and if you
look at
the history of how Watson was developed
and how Syrian Google now they're
constantly having those iterations of
hey yes the user like this no the user
dint like this right and so that that
feedback loop is critical and actually
you know to tie it back into the earlier
question about how we learn it's very
similar right we get feedback from our
parents from our teachers from books
from you know whatever it is that you
know dispel or reinforce particular
ideas and behaviors but then what what
is the difference between simply
learning and artificial intelligence
like computers that think in inverted
commas for themselves that's a great
question I mean I you know I think
obviously the Turing test is one example
there which we talked about earlier you
know it's probably more of a
philosophical discussion over beers as
to whether a computer ever can you know
think or behave you know and and be
human if you will if that's the ultimate
goal which you know I would I personally
don't care whether it is or not I mean I
think it'd be interesting but you know
to me I want systems that help
complement like I said earlier what what
we're doing you know like I said as far
as whether there's true artificial
intelligence someday or not you know I
guess that remains to be seen my bet is
that there will be but you know I don't
I don't know when or where or how
although we have touched it a bit before
I would like to again discuss the last
chapter of your book one topic that
stood out for me was understanding the
meaning of bigger texts here you used to
term this cause a lot could you please
explain the term and why it is part of
the bigger challenges in taming text
yeah I mean I think you know when you
start to talk about those higher-level
parts of language you know you're
looking at how do you incorporate world
knowledge how do you incorporate all the
you know all of the things that are left
on said or on written how do you account
for you know the fact that I know
some jargon and you don't or vice versa
or how do you account for the generation
gap between people right you know so I
think you know trying to process and
understand the meaning at that higher
level can be really helpful for more
effectively communicating as people
right I mean if you just think about how
many things go wrong in this world by
the fact that there's some gap or
impedance mismatch or or noise in the
channel if you will between people right
I mean if you had ways to help smooth
that over or help other people
understand the those gaps better it
seems to me and you know it's obviously
perhaps a little bit pie in the sky but
it seems to me that you have a real
opportunity to help people you know at
the end of the day get along better
right but also understand each other
better and ultimately help the computers
understand us better as well and so you
know I think there's some really hard
challenges there frankly they're you
know one of the reasons that's in the in
that chapter of the on time section is
there's just now starting to be some you
know work that is getting traction in
helping computers understand those
layers and and so you're starting to see
some tools emerge there I'm not
intimately familiar with any of them but
I've you know essentially seen some
discussions on them but you know it's
it's a really hard problem I mean just
think about two humans trying to do it
right and how often we disagree right so
if we can't agree how would we expect a
computer to agree when when they're just
doing essentially what we told them to
do yeah everybody with a spouse can kids
and one big gap is actually produced by
people talking in different languages
and this is a challenge as well
are there approaches to face that and
how is this done yeah I mean there's
that is it's one of the first problems I
actually worked on in search and it's
it's kind of ironic because if you think
about searches being a hard problem
cross language search and cross language
understanding is even bigger right and
so you know short of getting everybody
to speak the language which you know the
fact that you're in Germany and I'm here
and we're both speaking English is you
know obviously there's some level of
effort happening that way you know
across the school systems and across the
world but you know also just being able
to have better machine translation all
of those things are kind of under way
and there's there's efforts going on
things like Google Translate there's
other engines out there that do similar
things you know so the kind of the
approaches for this you know obviously
having people do it is really costly it
tends to be pretty highly accurate but
it doesn't scale very well and so then
you often look at how can computers
supplement that there are student you
know purely statistical approaches which
just essentially take in two large
bodies of parallel text you know if you
think about it like for instance the
United Nations publishes all of its
documents in you know I don't even know
how many different languages and so
those are effectively parallel texts
right and so presumably you can line
them up statistically speaking and
figure out that you know this phrase in
German is so often correlates with a
certain phrase in English right and so
then over time you're learning those
statistical patterns
there are also rule-based patterns you
know let's say if you ever see this kind
of phrase in or sentence type or
sentence structure in German then you
know that coincides with this kind of
phrase in English or in Spanish or fill
in the blank and so you know I mean I
think most systems kind of take a hybrid
approach which is they have some
statistical models that they are
grounded in and cover most of the
language
then they have rules that they overlay
that deal with the exceptions right you
know because I think like especially in
English we have the saying you know the
exception that proves the rule right
there's so many exceptions and irregular
verbs and things like that
you have computers headaches if you will
of course are there some scientific
approaches on analyzing German as a
language and to say then okay this is a
proper noun in German and then being
able to map this on Spanish or Japanese
which would be really hard there's some
approaches in this area as well you know
this is where like you know like a
Google Translate approach is just hey
let me look at you know millions and
millions of examples or thousands and
thousands of examples whatever it is and
so it's it's it's you know I guess
scientifically speaking it's a
statistical approach if you will you
know there's obviously linguists and and
people who study you know do nothing but
study a particular language or even a
sub part of the language all day every
day
I'm not one of those people but there
are thankfully there are those people
out there and you know so you can go to
things like the Association for
computational linguistics and the like
and and really dig into those soon so
yeah there are people who are studying
German at you know as a language and
then of course they're they try to put
it in the context of a common language
that you know all linguists are studying
and so you know we try to map the
concepts across those you know across
the languages but you know the that's
the that's one of the cool things about
languages too is there's often just some
concepts that that don't translate and
you know I mean I think ultimately
that's what makes us human but also
ultimately what makes it even more
difficult for the likes of us who are
trying to you know study this and make
the computer understand this kind of
stuff yeah getting a bit away from your
book I'd like to ask you if there is a
feature or if there are features of
mahouts oh learn the scene that are
inverted commas outstanding because you
chose them in the in the book but even
further and it's Dow outstanding meaning
without any equal feature in commercial
projects or even Google there's
something you can say okay
you soul are because this and that and
you won't find it anywhere else well
first off I don't know what's going on
in Google so you know I obviously can't
compare there you know it's interesting
I think probably the most outstanding
feature of all three of them is an
intangible one which is that they're
community developed open-source and so
not only is their code that you know is
held to a pretty high rigor it may or
may not be as good as you know Google or
Bing or the like but you know ultimately
as an engineer I can go look at it
and I can dig into it and I can decide
that hey if I don't like that particular
piece but I like all the rest of this I
can change it and so there's a really
powerful community around all of those
things one of the best things I say
about my how it is you know regardless
of whether you actually want to use our
particular algorithms that we've
implemented there's a community there
that is really interested in this stuff
and so if you just go and ask a question
chances are you'll find somebody who can
help you and and sometimes we even tell
them hey you know go use some other tool
because we think it's better and so I
think that community aspect and the
openness is probably the you know
without equal feature anywhere you know
just by you know kind of by definition
right as for you know the technical
features it's been interesting an open
source I mean I think you know for a
long time open source was all about
commoditizing commercial features
whereas nowadays I think you're seeing a
lot of innovation happening in in the
open source but again you know I mean I
don't study every Pat and I don't study
every commercial project so I don't know
exactly what's going on I do know like
in leucine and solar we've done some
really interesting things around
compression and term representing the
term dictionaries in efficient way we've
been using things like finite Stata Tom
otamatone and the like in really
interesting ways to help solve search
problems I think we probably on the
solar side we can probably scale more
economically than anybody else meaning
that the not only can we technically
scale just to meet the demands of the
amount of data you have but you can
actually afford to do that because
you're not paying exorbitant licensing
fees so you know so like I said I mean a
lot of this comes down to a mixture of
really strong technical features with
this incredible openness model that
ultimately leads to the sum of the parts
being more than you know all you know
the earth sorry the the the whole of the
parts is worth more than the sum of them
right I'm totally butchering that's you
know so like like it's it's the
combination of them over any one
individual feature is probably where I
would say you know is really the thing
that stands out you said that and I
quote we are good at and we have been
doing good in this then how did you
actually get involved in developing for
those projects and starting Apache
mahout yeah a little bit of a long story
but I'll save a little bit so with
leucine I literally walked in the door
at Center for natural language
processing you know I'd been using open
source for you know since 1999 or
whatever I walked in the door in 2004
with some people that I worked for
before but we actually used a
proprietary engine previously and I was
asked to implement an Arabic English
cross language search engine
and I walked in the door my boss said we
usually scene go figure it out I said
okay and we started I started digging in
and learning it and as I was learning it
there were some things that I knew knew
I needed to implement in my application
that
Lusine didn't do and I got permission
from my boss to implement those things
obviously because I needed them but not
only did I get permission to implement
them I got permission to give them back
to the community and and so if nothing
else maybe perhaps it demystifies the
open source process but you know what
happens is if you keep doing that you
know pretty soon the people who are
responsible for the codebase say hey you
know we trust you or they say hey I'm
tired of reviewing your patches or your
contributions I trust what you're doing
I'm going to give you the rights to
contribute those and so that's how I got
involved with Lucene and then you know
interesting enough I think how it
actually came out of Lusine you know I
had emailed I think I forget actually
when it was 2006 2007 I had emailed the
dev list one day and said hey you know
this machine learning stuff is starting
to heat up I think it could be you know
there's a lot of interesting uses for it
in the search space would it be great if
the Lucene project had you know a much
broader scope beyond just search and
actually took on and incorporated things
like machine learning and natural
language processing and I sent that
email and I think pretty much nobody
responded and then a year later actually
this woman Isabelle droste actually a
fellow German emailed me and said hey
are you still interested in this and I
said of course and so her and I started
emailing back and forth and you know we
started to kind of expand the net of
people who we thought in the Lucene
community would be interested in this
and out of it formed you know
essentially a small working group to
kind of figure out what what we should
do and at that same time Andrew Ning
many people know from Coursera on the
my machine learning course out of
Stanford I had published along with some
of his students a paper on ten
algorithms that you could implement ten
machine learning algorithms that you
could implement in MapReduce and you
know Hadoop was just starting to take
off and so we had read that paper and
and we said hey would it be great if we
started a project at Apache that solved
you know that implemented these
algorithms because these are kind of the
tried-and-true machine learning
algorithms and a way we went you know
the other need we had is a lot of the
machine learning libraries at the time
we did not like their license on them
you know for better for worse we didn't
feel they were licenses that our work
would allow us to use and so we wanted
an Apache License project we also wanted
better documentation and and we wanted
to build up a community around that
codebase all things which you know the
Apache Software Foundation are very good
at and so you know we proposed this to
the Lucene project management committee
they accepted we started the project and
then I think about a year or two later
we actually spun it out as its own
top-level project and you know it is
where it is now there's you know pretty
decent sized community there there's a
lot of interesting development work
going on and you know it's kind of
taking on a life of its own can you
think of some topics that are actually
open right now and you need help and
maybe our listeners can step in and help
you out on the outside I mean I think
right now you know what's happening in
the community there and to be honest I'm
I'm not as involved in my out as I used
to be frankly but you know I still do
try to stay involved you know right now
we're in the process of you know a lot
of the algorithms that we did originally
were based off of hadoop mapreduce these
algorithms are iterative by nature and
in you know the old way of doing
MapReduce that was very expensive so
there's been a real push as of late
towards distributed approaches that
aren't as iterative in nature
or at least better at dealing with
iterative algorithms so things like
spark if you're familiar with that
project and the like we also have some
effort underway in terms of just
bringing in new approaches and
calculations you know so there's if
you're really hardcore you know really
good programmer really good at math etc
you can really get into the algorithms
at a very deep level and that's one way
you can help on Mount but frankly
there's also just a real need for people
who can do documentation who can fix
bugs who can explain use cases who can
write examples who can make it easier
for for people to get data in and out of
the out of the system and so you know
there's lots of different ways you can
contribute on the how same goes for
leucine and solar you know there's
there's obviously core algorithms that
are really interesting and often require
you know pretty deep knowledge around
performance and quality but there's just
also a whole lot of low-hanging fruit in
terms of bugs and use cases and examples
and documentation and so you know one of
the things I think I often find people
will ask me how do I contribute to open
source and and they have some bit of
trepidation around it and you know I
really encourage them to just start with
something small and simple get their
feet wet you know start asking questions
start answering questions and then as
you grow with the system you'll you'll
feel more and more comfortable with it
and ultimately that can be a real boon
to your your career and your your ear
skills as a programmer
okay so listeners you encouraged to go
to the website of mahouts and solar and
you're seen and start working on it yeah
just ask on the mailing list to hey you
know I've got some spare time where can
I help out you know go I think all of
those pages all of those websites have a
how to contribute page on them so if you
just google solar how to contribute or
mahou how to contribute you know chances
are the first link will be a page that
says hey here's how you check out the
code here's how you create patches or
pull requests
or here's where we keep our
documentation here's what we expect of
you from unit tests and so you can get
lots of information that way and and it
really isn't as as scary as it sometimes
sounds all right my last question is did
you forget something and well we we
spoke about the second edition of your
book is there something else in the
pipeline are you speaking at conferences
in the future some if people want to
hear from you hear you talk see your
work where can they meet and how can
they contact you and the hardest
question of them all what didn't you ask
you know I think I think we covered a
lot of good things I mean I think
looking at the upcoming edition we're
gonna add in some new and interesting
topics like sentiment analysis
summarization visualization of text so
there's some really interesting things
coming up yes very interesting topics
which is why I'm really looking forward
to reading the second edition all right
since we reached the end of our episode
I want to say thanks for being on the
show again and talking about your book
taming text it has been a real pleasure
Thank You Tobias glad to be here again
in addition to grant I want to thank you
listeners for downloading this episode
we want to know what you think about
this show and how we can improve there
are various ways of telling us you can
go to iTunes or our website and write a
review of this episode or leave general
comments and I would encourage you to
doing so this is to be as cards for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to s-see radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise SU radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
please see the website for details
thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]